<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>HPC Python</title>
    <link>https://jstaf.github.io/hpc-python/</link>
    <description>Recent content on HPC Python</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 23 Apr 2016 15:21:22 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://jstaf.github.io/hpc-python/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Pipelining with Python</title>
      <link>https://jstaf.github.io/hpc-python/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Apr 2016 15:21:22 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jstaf.github.io/hpc-python/</guid>
      <description>Python is probably the most versatile language in existence. However one of its most useful features is its ability to tie things together and automate the execution of other programs.
This tutorial focuses on using Python in HPC environments to automate data analysis pipelines. We&amp;rsquo;ll start with the basics and cover everything you need to get started writing pipelines. Some elements of writing performance-oriented code will be covered, but it is not the main focus.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Basic syntax</title>
      <link>https://jstaf.github.io/hpc-python/basics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jstaf.github.io/hpc-python/basics/</guid>
      <description>The most basic use of Python is to use it as a fancy calculator. It is very easy to do basic math in Python.
print(5 + 1)  6  Note that we don&amp;rsquo;t always have to use the print() statement. Notice how leaving out print() gives us the same result as above.
5 + 1  6  Python can do all of the normal basic math operations you&amp;rsquo;d expect.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Scripts and imports</title>
      <link>https://jstaf.github.io/hpc-python/scripts/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jstaf.github.io/hpc-python/scripts/</guid>
      <description>Everything we&amp;rsquo;ve learned so far is pretty cool. But if we want to run a set of commands more than once? How do we write a program in Python?
Python programs are simply a set of Python commands saved in a file. No compiling required! To demonstrate this, let&amp;rsquo;s write our first program! Enter the following text in a text editor and save it under any name you like (Python files are typically given the extension .</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>